<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cantica Certen of the songes of HN. To a good instruction and edifyinge of the Famelie of Loue, and of all those that turne them ther-vnto. Translated out of Base-almayne.</title>
            <author>Niclaes, Hendrik, 1502?-1580?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18549</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113258</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848495</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13591</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08214)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13591)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 325:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cantica Certen of the songes of HN. To a good instruction and edifyinge of the Famelie of Loue, and of all those that turne them ther-vnto. Translated out of Base-almayne.</title>
                  <author>Niclaes, Hendrik, 1502?-1580?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N. Bohmberg,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cologne :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1575]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>HN = Hendrik Niclaes.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>German original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Familists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13591:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13591:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CANTICA.</hi> Certen of the Songes of <hi>HN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To a good Inſtruction and Edifyinge of the Famelie of Loue / and of all thoſe that turne them ther-vnto.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Baſe-almayne.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">CORONAE ASSIMILABO IVDICIVM MEVM <bibl>4 ESD 5</bibl>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:yhwh">יהוה</g>
               </p>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <q>Teach and exhort one-another of you, with Pſalmes and Hymnes, and with ſpirituall Songes: and ſinge vnto the Lorde in your Heartes. <bibl>Col. 3. b. Iam. 5. b.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:13591:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13591:2"/>
            <head>The Firſt Songe. For to complaine; with ſorrowfull Singinge; ouer the Sinne, and to praye vnto God.</head>
            <lg>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Wake now<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 35.44.</note> O Lorde to mee / </l>
               <l>Vnſtop thine Eares likewiſe:</l>
               <l>My Heart I turne to thee / </l>
               <l>Harken to<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 54. a. 55 61.64.86.88.</note> my Plaint and Cryes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>The Bourdaine<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 38.40. a 51.</note> of my Sinnes vnrite / </l>
               <l>Maketh my Heart out of eaſe:</l>
               <l>My Heauines muſt I rezite / </l>
               <l>If it mought ⁏O Lorde; thee pleaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>But<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 69. a.</note> turne to mee thine Eye / </l>
               <l>Beholde my<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 31. b.</note> greeuous Caſe:</l>
               <l>Let not the Sinne leade mee awrye / </l>
               <l>Inlardge ouer mee thy Grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>O Lorde / behold my<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 25.55.</note> Sorrowe &amp; Paine / </l>
               <l>Together with my Heauineſſe:</l>
               <l>Thy Comfort<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 86.</note> let mee now obtaine / </l>
               <l>In this my great Diſtreſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> 5.</head>
               <l>The Euell hath<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 88. g.</note> caught my Heartes Luſt / </l>
               <l>And brought mee into Miſerie more:</l>
               <l>I longe for the<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 79. b.</note> Deliueraunce iuſt / </l>
               <l>O Lorde / deferre it not therfore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Purifie<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 51. Ezec. 36.</note> ⁏O Lorde; my Hart / </l>
               <l>And geeue mee thy Spirit of reſt:</l>
               <l>The Euell bringeth<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal 69. b. Eſa. 54. b.</note> mee Smart / </l>
               <l>And maketh in mee tempeſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Mought I liue in the Good which doth laſt / </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13591:3"/>So had my Soule then reſt preſent:</l>
               <l>Now hath the Sinne clouen to mee faſt / </l>
               <l>To thee ⁏O Lorde; is my<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 40. b.</note> Luſt bent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> 8.</head>
               <l>Let mee not now<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 26.</note> go to decaye / </l>
               <l>Nor perriſh with the wicked Man:</l>
               <l>Thy Loue let mee poſſeſſe, I praye / </l>
               <l>That I<note n="o" place="margin">Sap. 5. a.</note> may ſtill before thee ſtan.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>9.</head>
               <l>Mought I walke in thy<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 25.27.</note> Pathes free / </l>
               <l>O Lorde / that would I very faine:</l>
               <l>What ſhould then<note n="q" place="margin">1. Pet. 3. b.</note> hinder or dammaige mee / </l>
               <l>For it were all to my great Gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>10.</head>
               <l>God ⁏Prince;<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 51. a.</note> ſhewe on mee thy Mercie / </l>
               <l>And in thy<note n="s" place="margin">Pſal. 17. b. 25 a. 27. b. 143. a</note> Pathes mee gide:</l>
               <l>Imbrace mee in thine Armes louelie / </l>
               <l>Or I ſhall neuer be ſatiſfide.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="song">
            <head>The II. Songe. For to pray ⁏with Singinge; vnto God, in the Sorrowfulnes ouer the Sinne, for to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſſed ther-from.</head>
            <lg>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/>
               <l>BOth Night and Day I am penſife / </l>
               <l>For my<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 31. b. 38. b. 88. a.</note> Sinnes that are ſo rife / </l>
               <l>How wofull am I:</l>
               <l>How wofull is my Soule / </l>
               <l>O God / let mee obtaine<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 6.51. a. 86.</note> Mercie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>O Lorde<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 51. a.</note> extend on mee thy Grace / </l>
               <l>I haue offended before thy Face / </l>
               <l>My<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 32. a.</note> Fault I confeſſe:</l>
               <l>In Hope<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 25.31.</note> and great Longinge / </l>
               <l>That thou wilt mee yet releſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> 3.</head>
               <l>A pure<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 51. Ezec. 11.18. c.</note> Heart geeue vs / O Lorde / </l>
               <l>Out of <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> accorde / </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13591:3"/>Thy Loue of-price:</l>
               <l>Geeue vs alſo that holie Beeinge / </l>
               <l>Purge<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 51. c.</note> vs from all our Sinne and Vice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>O Lorde / <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 40.70.</note> to healp vs make now ſpeede / </l>
               <l>The Sinne bringeth mee in great dreede / </l>
               <l>Therfore I lament:</l>
               <l>Therfore I<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 25. b.</note> lament now bitterlie / </l>
               <l>O God heare mee at this preſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> 5.</head>
               <l>O God / my Lorde / what are all wee / </l>
               <l>Wilt thou ſet thyſelf<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 130. a.</note> againſt mee / </l>
               <l>For my Treſpas:</l>
               <l>My Treſpaſſe for to recompence / </l>
               <l>So are my Woorkes<note n="l" place="margin">Eſa. 64. c.</note> all euell ⁏alas;.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Prince of Heauen / O Lorde gentell / </l>
               <l>Releaſſe vs<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 18. a.</note> from the Sinne / Death / and Hell / </l>
               <l>Make vs now free:</l>
               <l>Make vs now<note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 1. g. Rom. 6.8. a.</note> free from the Sinne / </l>
               <l>And plucke our Spirit to thee.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="song">
            <head>The V. Songe. To a Warninge of the Famelie of Loue / for the auoydinge of the Deſtruction.</head>
            <lg>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/>
               <l>PAſſe-by and ſtirre not<note n="a" place="margin">Eſa. 56. b.</note> the ſleaping Hounde / </l>
               <l>Waken them not / that is my Counſell.</l>
               <l>So bide then to their Mouthes vnſound / </l>
               <l>And yee defended from their Euell:</l>
               <l>Thus<note n="b" place="margin">Math. 7. c.</note> beware of their wicked Deede fell / </l>
               <l>So ſhall they then bite you no Wounde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Feare not therfore the young Houndes Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge ſtill:</l>
               <l>But beware of their Elders Enuye ⁏wide;.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13591:4"/>Likewiſe alſo of their Rebukinge ill.</l>
               <l>For their Rebuke ⁏on euery ſide;</l>
               <l>Mendeth noman / at any tide / </l>
               <l>No<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 59. b.</note> good at-all prepare they will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> 3.</head>
               <l>All wilde Beares / &amp; whining Swine vnpure / </l>
               <l>All ſliringe Wolues / with their cruell Fierſnes / </l>
               <l>And they that deride the louelie Nature / </l>
               <l>And diſpiſe her Vertue / with Wickednes / </l>
               <l>All that vſe no Reaſonablenes / </l>
               <l>Among thoſe appere not / nor their Companie enure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Although they ſpake all / as with a<note n="d" place="margin">Math. 7. c.</note> Lambes Tounge / </l>
               <l>And complained ſore of their Let / </l>
               <l>So is it yet for themſelues all ſounge / </l>
               <l>And you from the Lawe to plucke or fet / </l>
               <l>To their peruerſe Nature, their wicked Net / </l>
               <l>That is not don of the Sheepes Younge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> 5.</head>
               <l>Of the horrible<note n="e" place="margin">Dan. 9. e. 11. c Math. 24. b.</note> Deſolation take you good heede / </l>
               <l>All wicked Beaſtes Lande-of-inheritaunce:</l>
               <l>And thoſe which enuie the Loues Seede / </l>
               <l>They are planted into Offence and Noyaunce / </l>
               <l>The<note n="f" place="margin">Eſa. 30. b. Ier. 7. c.</note> Good-thinkinge is their Plaiſaunce / </l>
               <l>And Wickednes their Reioycinge indeede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Whoſo from the Loues Doctrine hath his Departinge / </l>
               <l>And ſo himſelf doth teach with his Skill / </l>
               <l>Hath euermore a great Longinge:</l>
               <l>But hee<note n="g" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> remaineth as contrarie ſtill.</l>
               <l>And through his Good-thinking &amp; peruerſe Will / </l>
               <l>Hee bideth captiued therin euerlaſtinge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> 7.</head>
               <l>Of all theſe Perrels great and ſmall / </l>
               <l>Take-heede with all your Thought and Might / </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13591:4"/>Haue nothinge common therwith at-all.</l>
               <l>But<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 1.2.</note> exerciſe you both Daye and Night / </l>
               <l>In the Seruice of Loue / and by her Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bright / </l>
               <l>Holde you alone, continuallie yee ſhall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Princes / if yee think to be aboue our Doctrine</l>
               <l>Yet exalt not your Heartes therin / in any-wiſe:</l>
               <l>But laude now the Lorde / with vs in our Line.</l>
               <l>Make alſo no Variaunce / heare my Deuiſe / </l>
               <l>Greeue<note n="i" place="margin">Eccli. 3. b.</note> not your Elder with your Practiſe.</l>
               <l>Ne robbe nothing from him at any time.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="song">
            <head>The XXI. Songe. Of the Manifeſtation or Declaring of the true Light of God and Chriſt in the Famelie of Loue, wherwith ther are many good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions witneſſed, which tende to the Loue and to her Ioye and Peace.</head>
            <lg>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/>
               <l>GOds Light will<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 5. b. Mark. 4.</note> hid no lenger bee / </l>
               <l>But riſeth now moſt-cleere to ſee / </l>
               <l>And ⁏from within; doth lighten Such / </l>
               <l>Whoſe Heartes / Gods Loue do fauour much: do fauour much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>On<note n="b" place="margin">Math. 5. b. Luk. 8. 11. b.</note> Candleſticke / doth now Gods Light / </l>
               <l>Stande ⁏liuinglie; ſo firme and bright / </l>
               <l>In that moſt-bleſſed Howſe of Loue / </l>
               <l>That none can euer it ⁏Thence; remoue: it thence remoue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Aſſemble yee Plantes ⁏both Hie and Lo; / </l>
               <l>And to<note n="e" place="margin">Eſa. 2. c 3. a. Iere. 50.</note> the Howſe of Loue / now go:</l>
               <l>For Therin may you Light comby / </l>
               <l>But neuer without theſame truly: theſame truly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> 4.</head>
               <l>Conſider ⁏in time; your great Miſery / </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13591:5"/>That yee all<note n="d" place="margin">Sap. 1. b. 16. c Apo. 3. b.</note> ⁏liuinge; are dead: for why / </l>
               <l>No Life can yee gett or obtaine / </l>
               <l>But through the Loue / that is moſt plaine: that is moſt plaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>For / without the Loue / 'tis a ſure caſe / </l>
               <l>The Darknes ⁏ouer-all; doth<note n="e" place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.</note> take the place:</l>
               <l>Alſo the Sectes / of Woorkes moſt-fell / </l>
               <l>Reſpect theſame now therfore well: now therfore well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>In the Darknes ⁏y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Deuels Lorde &amp; Head?</l>
               <l>They are ſtill more-and-more / in<note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 5. c. 9. b.</note> Errour lead / </l>
               <l>Which now contemne Gods Loue ⁏ſo hye; / </l>
               <l>Wherin they all releefles dye: releefles dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> 7.</head>
               <l>God is therfore / the<note n="g" place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.</note> Loue amorus / </l>
               <l>Which now ⁏in Loue; liueth ſo in vs:</l>
               <l>And / in all<note n="h" place="margin">Ephe. 4. Col. 3. b.</note> Concorde / to be vaunced hie / </l>
               <l>That is ⁏in Loue; grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ſurelie: grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ſurelie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Heer-with in God / ioye wee vnlet / </l>
               <l>Loue to enure / is<note n="i" place="margin">Deut. 6. Math. 22. d. Iohn. 13.15.</note> his Precept:</l>
               <l>Eake the Fulfillinge / of Gods Lawe vnfained / </l>
               <l>Yea / th'whole Scripture / which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained: <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ordained.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>9.</head>
               <l>O Princes of God ⁏both great and ſmall; / </l>
               <l>Publiſh-fourth this Light / now generall / </l>
               <l>Which God ⁏in Vs; hath ſo expreſſed / </l>
               <l>The Liuers in Loue / are ſurelie bleſſed: are ſurelie bleſſed.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="song">
            <head>The XXX. Songe. For to be ſounge with Ioye, of the Goodnes of the Life, in the ſweete New-yeare.</head>
            <lg>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:13591:5"/>
               <l>THe Time is com euen-now about / </l>
               <l>God hath his Woorke / perfectlie dight.</l>
               <l>Now<note n="a" place="margin">Eſa. 25.67. Apo. 21.</note> taken is / from vs no-dout / </l>
               <l>Oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all / and Heartes-greefe quight.</l>
               <l>The<note n="b" place="margin">Agg. 1. b. Rom. 2.</note> Peace / to vs is geeuen rife / </l>
               <l>All verteous Loue doth eake appeere / </l>
               <l>All verteous Loue doth eake appeere:</l>
               <l>Therto<note n="c" place="margin">Math. 25. Iohn. 6.17.</note> th'euerlaſtinge Life / </l>
               <l>Al-in this louelie ſweete New-yeere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Let each-one now beholde and ſee / </l>
               <l>Gods Woorkes / and his Counſell good:</l>
               <l>Buylde now vpon the Loue / al-free / </l>
               <l>Receaue her holie Seede (to Food).</l>
               <l>Come you to<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 12. 1. Cor. 12. c.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi>-his Members / ſo / </l>
               <l>Euen in the Howſe of Loue / moſt-cleere / </l>
               <l>Euen in the Howſe of Loue / moſt-cleere:</l>
               <l>Then ſhall yee liue in Peace ⁏from wo; / </l>
               <l>Al-in this louelie ſweete New-yeere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> 3.</head>
               <l>Keepe now thy<note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 21.</note> Heart / both faſt and ſure / </l>
               <l>⁏Thou manlie Generation ſtill;</l>
               <l>From all Surmiſinges-race / vnpure / </l>
               <l>Alſo from<note n="f" place="margin">Sapi. 1.</note> Cogitations ill:</l>
               <l>But print well in thy Minde / this thinge / </l>
               <l>The Life of the heauenlie Company heere / </l>
               <l>The Life of the heauenlie Company heere:</l>
               <l>And let thatſame / be thy Winninge / </l>
               <l>Al-in this louelie ſweete New-yeere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Wheron-ſoeuer thou art bounde / </l>
               <l>Wherin alſo thy Pleaſure doth ſtande / </l>
               <l>Together with all thy Sinnes / vnſounde / </l>
               <l>Bringe all thatſame / in<note n="g" place="margin">Pro. 28. b. Eccl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4. c.</note> Th'elders Bande:</l>
               <l>So ſhalt thou liue vncaptiued beſt / </l>
               <l>In Peace / without all Perrill and Feere / </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13591:6"/>In Peace / without all Perrill and Feere / </l>
               <l>And ſhalt ful-well<note n="h" place="margin">4. Eſd. 2. c. Math. 11. c</note> obtaine the Reſt / </l>
               <l>Al-in this louelie ſweete New-yeere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> 5.</head>
               <l>The Worldes Variaunce<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 16. b. Col. 2.</note> and Chyding fell / </l>
               <l>Plucke thou thatſame / in no-caſe on:</l>
               <l>The falſe Teachers Drifte and Counſell / </l>
               <l>Turne thou thine Eares / alwaye therfrom:</l>
               <l>But euer bow you downe ful-milde / </l>
               <l>And coupple you ſo to the Loue / right-deere / </l>
               <l>And coupple you ſo to the Loue / right-deere:</l>
               <l>Her Breaſtes to<note n="k" place="margin">Eſa. 66. b.</note> ſucke ⁏euen as her Childe;</l>
               <l>Al-in this louelie ſweete New-yeere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Yee Princes all / wake now vpp ⁏meete; / </l>
               <l>Laude God / in<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 105.</note> his great Actes ful-hie:</l>
               <l>Approch now to the Loue, ſo ſweete / </l>
               <l>Her<note n="m" place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> heauenlie Bread / taſt preſentlie:</l>
               <l>Receaue her Guiftes and great Goodnes / </l>
               <l>In Thankeſgeeuing<note n="n" place="margin">1. Cor. 10. Col. 3. b.</note> / with Merie-cheere / </l>
               <l>In Thankeſgeeuing / with Merie-cheere:</l>
               <l>So ſhall ſhee you ſuſtaine / doubtles / </l>
               <l>Al-in this louelie ſweete New-yeere.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="31" type="song">
            <head>The XXXI. Songe. For to be ſounge with Ioye, of the vpright Godlynes, which is com ⁏from God-his Grace; vnto the Famelie of Loue.</head>
            <lg>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/>
               <l>SAluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Health / &amp; all Peace good / </l>
               <l>Lucke and Ioye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lifes Sweet-mood / </l>
               <l>Cometh vnto them with Bleſſinge / </l>
               <l>Which now<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 10. c. 30. b. Math. 22. c.</note> with all their Heartes Blood / </l>
               <l>Are inclyned to the louelie Beeinge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Whoſo letteth theſame now appeere / </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13591:6"/>With the Deede / out of the Loues Doctrine heere / </l>
               <l>Shall<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn. 25. b.</note> keepe the Loue with Heart and Minde:</l>
               <l>And alſo followe her Counſell cleere / </l>
               <l>And<note n="c" place="margin">Math. 24. c. Iohn. 10. b. 17. c.</note> congregate him to her Kinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>The right Doctrine of the Loue pure / </l>
               <l>Is now taught out of Loue plaine and ſure / </l>
               <l>With ſweete Gaine / to euery Nation / </l>
               <l>And is miniſtred now alone ⁏to dure;</l>
               <l>Out of the Loues Congregation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> 4.</head>
               <l>Ther came to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Worlde neuer greater Light / </l>
               <l>Then <hi>Chriſtes</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 13. b. 1. Cor. 13. a.</note> Loue / with his cleere Sight / </l>
               <l>Let yourſelues therin be taught ⁏freelye;.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Chriſtes</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Col. 3. b.</note> Peace becom edified right / </l>
               <l>And in theſame do yee multiplye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Theſe are ⁏doubtles; Gods<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 17.21. b.</note> Promiſes fine / </l>
               <l>Which are promiſed to <hi>Iſraels</hi> Line / </l>
               <l>To our Releaſſinge now therby / </l>
               <l>That wee in the Loues bright<note n="g" place="margin">Mal. 4. a.</note> Sunne-ſhine / </l>
               <l>Mought be bleſſed euerlaſtingly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>No ſweeter Nature nor better<note n="h" place="margin">Sap. 3.5. a. Heb. 3.4. a.</note> Reſt / </l>
               <l>Then is to Vs now out of Loue expreſt / </l>
               <l>For to liue alwayes therin well.</l>
               <l>Go-fourth therin now vnmoleſt / </l>
               <l>And tremble nomore for the Euell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> 7.</head>
               <l>From thiſſame<note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 1.2. a. 3.4. a. 1. Tim. 1. a.</note> Doctrine by you inlargeed / </l>
               <l>Wherin yee can becom prepareed / </l>
               <l>Do not in any caſe<note n="k" place="margin">2. Tim. 3. b.</note> parte-awaye:</l>
               <l>Regarde not alſo an others Deed / </l>
               <l>So can noman then leade you aſtraye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Becom comforted in the God of Might / </l>
               <l>Be diligent in this Purpoſe right / </l>
               <l>With verteous Manners good and gaye:</l>
               <l>Woorke now with Vs in the Harueſt in-ſight / </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13591:7"/>But minde <hi rend="sup">l</hi> to hallowe Gods Sabboth alwaye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> 9.</head>
               <l>When the ſix Dayes accompliſhed bee / </l>
               <l>With your Woorkes / according to Gods Decree / </l>
               <l>Then cometh with Honour trulye / </l>
               <l>⁏For to ſanctifie with all Might free;</l>
               <l>The great<note n="m" place="margin">Eſa. 66. c.</note> Sabboth of the Lorde moſt-hye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>10.</head>
               <l>O Princes of God / with-out Feare quight / </l>
               <l>Loue all what God now doth beare with Might / </l>
               <l>Minde not to ſhrinke from theſe Wayes.</l>
               <l>For the Loues<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 118. c.</note> Day which pleaſeth God aright / </l>
               <l>Will ſhine about Vs now in all Dayes.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="rondel">
            <head>A Rondell of HN.</head>
            <l>IN our Seruice / with this Woorke pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent / </l>
            <l>Wee ſerue the Man to Loue and Peace rife:</l>
            <l>For Loue and Peace is our Foundament.</l>
            <l>In our Seruice / with this Woorke preſent / </l>
            <l>Wee haue turned vs to the Man ⁏out of good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent;</l>
            <l>With the Loue / <note n="*" place="margin">Tob. 4. Math. 7.</note> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as wee would be don to ⁏with out ſtrife;</l>
            <l>In our Seruice / with this Woorke preſent / </l>
            <l>Wee ſerue the Man to Loue and Peace rife / </l>
            <l>And wiſh him then therto / the euerlaſtinge Life.</l>
            <byline>CHARITAS EXTORSIT PER HN.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:13591:7"/>
            <head>A GIRDELL.</head>
            <l>WHen Life and Trueth / in Heart are pure / </l>
            <l>And Loue al-preſt / to take their part / </l>
            <l>Girt-faſt with Faith and Iuſtice ſure / </l>
            <l>To woorke ⁏in Man; Redreſſe of Hart:</l>
            <l>Wherby all Good / in Vnitie / </l>
            <l>Mought ⁏flouriſhinglie; in Peace beare-ſwaye / </l>
            <l>And Sinne ⁏ther-through; away to flie / </l>
            <l>To Gods due Prayſe / in Man / that Daye:</l>
            <l>How happie ſhall hee then be founde / </l>
            <l>That ſo girt is / in ſeemlie-guyſe / </l>
            <l>With ſuch a Girdell of Vertues ſounde / </l>
            <l>Wher-euer hee cometh amonge the Wyſe.</l>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> 
               <list>
                  <item>Beare it,, and weare it,, <hi>euer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Teare it,, ne peare it,, <hi>neuer.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:13591:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13591:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Now goeth the Iudgment ouer the World: Now becometh the Prince of this World caſt-out.</q>
               <bibl>Iohn. 12.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>allegorical depiction of the Lamb of God destroying sin</figDesc>
                  <p>The Waye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Trueth and the Life.</p>
                  <p>VICTORIA</p>
                  <p>Sinne.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Now is the Saluation / the Power / and the Kingdom / becom our Gods: and the Might his Chriſtes.</q>
               <bibl>Apoca. 12.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
